Guide to the Ida Noyes Papers 1854-1907
University of Chicago Library
Noyes, Ida. Papers
1854-1907
2 linear ft. (4 boxes.)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Ida Noyes, artist, philanthropist. The Ida Noyes Papers consist of 611 photographs, a postcard, and four bound volumes of letters from Ida Noyes to her husband, La Verne Noyes.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions.
Biographical Note
Ida Elizabeth Smith Noyes was born on April 16, 1853 in Croton, Delaware County, New York to Joel W. and Susan M. Wheat Smith. The family of seven moved to Iowa in 1857. In 1870 Noyes began attending Iowa State College, then spent a term at the State University of Iowa City, finally completing college at the State University at Ames in 1874.
Noyes returned home and became a teacher in the Charles City High School. She married La Verne Noyes, an inventor and manufacturer whom she had met in college, on May 24, 1877. The couple moved to Chicago in 1879, where Noyes followed her ambition to become an artist by enrolling at the Art Institute. This interest in art led her to make a two-year trip to Europe in 1886. In a volume of the University Record from 1919, Thomas W. Goodspeed writes that driven by her artistic instinct, Noyes was “a devotee of the camera” during her years in Europe.
Noyes made other trips, including an 1892 journey to the Pacific Coast where she visited Oregon, Washington, and California. She returned to Europe in 1894, and again in 1895. In the summer of 1897, Noyes and her husband took a trip throughout the West and Northwest of the United States, eventually ending up in Alaska. Later that same year, Noyes and a friend left to spend six months traveling around the world, having been inspired by a similar journey described in East, West-Home’s Best, by Sarah A. Pope. During this trip, Noyes took almost two thousand photographs. Other travels followed, and in 1910 Noyes made her last trip abroad to London.
Noyes, in addition to having a great love for travel, was very interested in the activities of women. She was the director of the Twentieth Century Club and of the Women’s Athletic Club. She was president of the North Side Art Club and was a member of the Chicago Colony of New England Women. Later, Noyes was an active member, then secretary and regent of the Daughters of the American Revolution, Chicago Chapter. Noyes went on to become the vice president of the national organization.
After a lengthy illness, Ida Noyes died on December 5, 1912. Six months after her death, her husband announced to the Trustees of the University of Chicago that he wanted to build a hall dedicated to her memory. The cornerstone for Ida Noyes Hall was laid on April 17, 1915.
Scope Note
The Ida Noyes Papers consist of 611 photographs, a postcard, and four bound volumes of letters from Ida Noyes to her husband, La Verne Noyes. The photographs were not taken by Noyes, but collected from various countries, including France, Italy, Egypt, Algeria, Israel, Turkey, Spain, India, Burma, and Japan. The letters contain descriptions of these foreign and other domestic journeys.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
See http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Subject Headings
Noyes, Ida Elizabeth Smith, 1853-1912; Noyes, La Verne W., 1849-1919; Voyages and travels; Voyages and travels -- Photographs; Women -- Travel; Letters; Photographs
INVENTORY
- SERIES I: Photographs
  - Riviera (1-5), Nice (6) Monaco (7-10) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Monte Carlo (11-17) Cannes (18-19) Menton (20-21) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Naples (22-31) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vesuvius (32-33) Syracuse (34-37) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Athens (38-55) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Egypt (?), Porte de la Citadelle et Mosquée Mouhammed Aly (56) Arab Fort and Cemetery (57) Articles made from palm fibers (58) Men with donkeys (59) Men and camels (60) Pots (61) Cairo: fishing boats (62-63) Village near the Pyramids (64) River boat (65) Bridge (66) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Egypt, Pyramid and Sphinx views (67-75) Ascending the Pyramid (76-77) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Egypt, Nile boats (78-79) Porter (80) Arab school (81) Woman from Cairo (82) woman and children (83) woman and child (84) man and shop (85) pottery shop (86) street scene (87) Obelisk of Heliopolis (88) Tree of the Virgin, Matarieh (89) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Egypt, women on cart (90) palm forest, Saqqara (91) statue of Ramses (92) Bedouins (93) Sheik (94) plowing with camels (95) plowing with a camel and ox (96) Nile boats (97) dam and waterwheel (98-99) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Egypt, Sakieh (100-101) Chadouf (102) Tomb of the Mameluks (103-104) Tomb of the Kalifs (105-106) Minarets (107) Cairo; mosque interiors (108-109) families in front of mosque (110) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Egypt and Turkey, Egyptian statues (111-115) Museum at Gizeh (116) river boat (117) Constantinople (118-122) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Interior of tombs of Sultans Mohammed and Aziz (123), Hagia Sophia (124-125) Tower (126) pompiers (firemen) (127) Bedouin girl (127a); dogs in street (128) seaside esplanade in Constantinople (129) view of Carthage (130) houses (131) Tunis (132) Kairouan, view of ramparts (133) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tunis, ancient street (134), Jewish Quarter (135) portrait of a man (136) [note: 137 not found] Bedouin women carrying their children (138) sons of Sheik Diab (139) laborers (140) Bedouin family (141) Saïd (142) selling shoes (143) Algiers (144) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Algiers (145-149), Museum of Algiers (150-151) Cathedral of Algiers (152) Algiers; interior of Winter Palace (153) Algiers (154) Algiers; Palace (155) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Algiers (156-157), portrait of woman (158-159) Chess players (160) excellent portraits of women (161-163) street scenes in Algiers (164-165) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Algiers, Algiers; courtyard view (166) Algiers; street view (167) Moorish cutter, Algiers (168) woman of Djeba (169) Caïd of Biskra (170) Cemetery, Algiers (171) Marabout (Sidi Yaya) (172) women at a cemetery (173) men by a building (174) tomb of a queen (175) fountain of Bougariah (176) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - North Africa and Spain, Notre Dame of Africa (177) Brook of monkeys (?) (178) Brook of monkeys, steeplechase (179) Granada; Alhambra and the Sierra Nevada (180) streets of the Alhambra (181) view of the tower of Vela and Granada (182) Granada; gate of Justice, interior view (183) Alhambra; Room of Justice (184) Alhambra; Gallery and Patio of the Leones next to the Room of Justice (185) view of Alhambra (186) view of the patio of Acequia (187) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Spain, Granada (188-198) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Spain, Granada (199-203) Seville (204-209) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Spain, Seville (210-220) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Spain, Oxen (221) painting on back (222) unidentified Spain (223) cathedral in Cordoba (224) unidentified Spain (225-227) Madrid (228-231) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Spain, Madrid (232-239) Toledo (240); Cougar (240a) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Israel, Jaffa (241-242) Mount of Olives (243) view of Jerusalem from Mount Scopus (244) Jaffa (245) Jerusalem (246-247) Mount of Olives (248-249) Road of the Captivity (250) Rachel's Tomb (251) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Israel, Church of the Nativity (252) General view of Bethlehem from David's wall (253) cave of the Nativity; the Manger (254) Tomb of David on Mt. Zion (255) Palestine (256) Hebron taken from the quarantine (257) general view of Hebron (258) General view of the mosque of Omar (Dome of the Rock) (259) interior of the mosque of Omar; the rock (Dome of the Rock) (260) the pulpit of Cadi Borhan-ed-Din (261) Jerusalem; view inside a church (262) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Israel, El-Aksa Mosque (263-264) Church of the Pater (265) Interior of the Holy Sepulchre (266) Station of the Cross 5 (267) unidentified Jerusalem (268) Jewish metalworker in Jerusalem (269) Guardian of the tomb of the kings and his family (270) Greek cathedral in the basilica (271) group of vegetable vendors; Jerusalem (272) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Israel, Plowing (273) sitting with guns by the lake (274) the Dead Sea and the hills of Judea (275) wall and golden gate, Jerusalem (276) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - India, Port Saïd (1) Waterfall at Penang (2) Jeypore; Maharaja's Palace (3) Jeypore; Jey Sing's conservatory (4) interior of Dewan-I-Kas Delhi (5) the Jumma Musjid, Dehli (6) section of the first and second stories of Tower of Victory, 12th c. (7) Dehli Gate-Agra Fort (8) Agra Fort from the River Jumma (9) Agra; the Fort (10) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - India, Moti Masjid (Pearl Mosque), Agra (11) Jama Masjud of Agra, built in 1644 by Shah Jahan (12) Agra; Taj Mahal (13) Sarcophagi in interior of Taj Agra (14) view of Taj from terrace of Wachhi Bhauran, Agra Fort (15) Another view of the Taj Mahal (16) Gateway of the Taj Mahal (17) Tomb, Agra (18) Agra; Mausoleum of Prince Etmad-Dowlah (19) inlaid and pierced marble in Itmad-ud-Daulat's tomb (20-21) Mosque interior s and exteriors (22-26) pillar in Dewan-I-Kass (27) general view of ruins (28) Outer Gate of Akbar's tomb, Sikaudra (29) memorial well, marble statue by Marochetti, Gawnpore (30) Lucknow, Modjibaman (31) unidentified temple (32) the sacred Ganges, at Benares, India (33) Benares; Rajah Potia Temple (34) Benares; Aurungzeb's Mosque (35) Benares; burning chat (36) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - India, Benares (37) Benares; Palace of Maharaja of Indore (38) Calcutta Maliks Ghat (39) Darjeeling; view from the Calcutta road looking towards the pole grounds (40) Darjeeling; view from Beechwood Park (41) Snowy range from Senghal, Everest on the left, Darjeeling, 1919 (42) Bridge over the Runjoo, Darjeeling, 1880 (43) source of the Ganges and ice cave at foot of the glacier (44) on the Ganges at Dangully (45); Chini and its mountains (46) from the Tibet Road, Pangi, Great Chini Peaks (47) the Spiti River at Kioto, Spiti (48) Top of Manirung Pass (49) Monastery at Ki, Spiti (50) Jhula Bridge across Spiti River (51) Mussucks (skin flotation devices) for crossing the Beas below Bajoura (52) view from rampore oak bungalow (53) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Burma, Carved temple on platform of Shura Dagon Pagoda, Rangoon (54) large reclining bronze Gautama in a temple on the platform of Shur Dagon Pagoda, Rangoon (55) General view from Mandalay showing "the 450 Pagodas" (56) Queen Soopayalat's silver Ryaung at Mandalay (57) Burmese pivay dance before Prince Albert Victor at Mandalay (58) street scene, Mandalay (59) Serpent temple, Mandalay (60) King Theebau's premier dancer (61) Burmese lady (62) Thai beauty (63) the 49 Gautamas in a temple at Sagaing (64) bazaar at Bhanno, on the Upper Irrawaddy, Burma (65) south of Indian, Madura-Gopura (66) kings of Ceylon and an Englishman (67) rubber tree, Peradeniya (68) Tanglin bungalows (69) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - China and Japan, Group of Chinese women (70) sedan chair of China (71) opium smokers in a Chinese restaurant (72) in Japanese waters (73) Nagasaki (74) Nagasaki (75) temple at Nagasaki (76) dining room with Japanese women (77) tying the obi (78); woman carrying a baby (79) woman looking into mirror (80) peasant at his work (81) girls dancing (82) singing girls (83) girls washing dresses (84) women sewing and ironing (85) women and children at a tea plantation (86) firing tea (87) girls playing cards (88) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Japan, Dancers (89) waterfall Nonobiki at Kobe (90) Oriental Hotel Kobe (91) Bund of Settlede at Kobe (92) view of Minatogawa (River), Kobe (93) Nara Park (94) Daibutsu Bell of Nara (95) view of Miyajima (96-97) Temple Gato Sumiyoshi at Osaka (98) Naniwabashi Bride (Osaka) (99) Matsushima Street at Osaka (100) Taikobashi (bridge) Sumiyoshi in Osaka (101) Osaka Castle (102) Nagoya Castle (103) Tennoji Pagoda, Osaka (104) Carp kites (105) Dancing girls holding umbrella (106) shell picking (107) rice fields of Japan (108) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Japan, Transplanting rice (109) blind masseur and shampooer (110) two pilgrims (111) women (112-114) a warrior fully armored (115) woman with hats (116) girls and a well (117) young nurse and her charge (118) women at a lotus pond (119) wayside tea house (120) hair dressing (121) woman with mirror (122) girls taking dinner (123) girl dressed for rain (124) Kiyomizu, at Kyoto (125-126) Maruyama Hotel, Kyoto (127) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Japan, Arashiyama; 3 teahouses, Kyoto (128) Arashiyama, Kyoto (129) Spectacle (Bridne) T Otani, Kioto (130) Gion-Macho, Kyoto (131) Sanjusangendo, Kyoto; An image of Buddha (132) Kurodani, Kyoto (133) Daibutsu Bell at Kyoto (134) Fushmi Inari, Kyoto, Shinto (135) Singing girls, Kyoto (136) Kiyomizu, at Kyoto (137) Kitano Temple at Kyoto (138) Gin Kakuji, Kyoto (139) Kin Kakuji, Kyoto (140) Japanese show shop (141) Singers (142) Cherry blossoms of Kogane (143) Arima Road (144) Tea house women (145) flower sellers (146) Codaido, Matsushima (147) Children's holiday (148) rope dancing (149) Daibutsu, Kamakura (150) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Japan, Kurodani Temple, Kyoto (151) Tower of Kiyomori, Hiogo (152) Fuji from Omiya (Tokaido) (153) Fujiyama from Yoshiwara, Tokaido (154) Fuiji from Taconoura (Tokaido) (155) View of evening at Maikonohama (156) Japanese junk (157) a scene at Hibiya to welcome emperor after the peace (158) a boat at Funaura, Nimadzu (159) festival car (160) European couple and ricksha (161) chair and cargo (162) Cooling vessel (163) Covered boat (Yanebune) (164) women sitting outside ("Coolness"), Kyoto (165) Pilgrims (166) girls washing hands by a stone basin (167) Dinner scene (168) girl with samisen (169) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Japan, Playing the Koto (170) singing girls (171-172) the Mikoshi (a portable shrine) (173) children in costume (174) woman at a loom (175) second hand clothing store (176) dancing girls (177) roadside teahouse (178) New Year's ceremony (179) tea ceremony (180) railway station, Yokohama (181) street scene, Yokohama (182) hill of Noge, Yokohama (183) Noge Hill, Yokohama (184) Sakuraya (Tea House), Honmoku, Yokohama (185) Yokohama Park during spring (186) Noge Hill at Yokohama (spring) (187-188) view of Yokohama (189) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Japan, Temple at Yokohama (190) creek side, Yokohama (191) 100 steps, Yokohama (192) Mississipy Bay, Yokohama (193) street scene, Yokohama (194) Noge Hill at Yokohama (195) cherry flower at Negishi, Yokohama (196) festival lanterns at Bentendori, Yokohama (197) railway station, Yokohama (198) imperial hotel at Tokyo (199) Mukojima Tokyo (200-201) Tea house at Mukojima, Tokyo (202) Mukojima, Tokyo (203) Kameido, Tokyo (204) Satake Garden, Mukojima, Tokyo (205) garden of the seat flag with irises (206) Akasaka, Tokyo (207) wisteria blossoms Kameido at Tokyo (208-209) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Japan, Tea house, Uyeno, Tokyo (210-211) girls, Kanagawa (212) wayside resting place at Mukojima, Tokyo (213) girls, Kanagawa (214) Oji, Tokyo (Maple) (215) Shiba at Tokyo (216) Haneda Temple near Tokyo (217) Jinrikisha at Cherry Aunue Kukojima, Tokyo (218) Ikegami Temple, near Tokyo (219) interior at Ikegami Temple, near Tokyo (220) Asakusa, Tokyo (221); bronze statues at Asakusa, Tokyo (222) dancing party (223) dancing at a banquet (224) dressing obi (225) showing backs of women's heads (226) bath scene (227) dressing scene (228) scene with ricksha (229) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Japan, Jinrkisha at Cherry Avenue, Mukojima, Tokyo (230) Nakasima tea house (231) doctor of writing (232) Fuji from Hakone LakeNaraya Hotel, Miyanoshita, Hakone (234) Fujiya, Miyanoshita (235) Fujiya Hotel (236) Gardeb at Hikone, Omi (237) Dogashima, Hakone (238-239) Daibutsu in Shinkoji, Hiogo (240) dancing girls holding an umbrella (241) pagoda at Hakone (242) Hakone Street (243) Kowajidani (hot spring) at Hakone (244) Fujiyama from Tagonura, Suruga (245) Annotated photograph; "To dear Mrs. L. Noyes with Sister Louise best compliments. Convent of the Holy Infant Jesus, Yokohama, consisting of 500 orphans, Tokio 200, Yokohama, 83 Bluff; Received in Nov. or December 1904, wrote letter of acknowledgement to Sister Louise" (246) Fujiyama from Otometoge (247) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Japan, Avenue of Cryptomerias (Japanese cedar) Nikko (248) approaching Yomeimon Gate (249) stone lanterns and gate of a temple, Nikko (250) sacred bridge at Nikko (251) stone steps, Nikko (252) Torii at Nikko (253) Yomeimon Gate, Nikko (254-255) carvings on the Yomeimon Gate, Nikko (256-257) Hear no evil, speak no evil, see no evil monkeys at Nikko (258-259) Lion at Yomeimon Gate (260) Wind Devil of Nitenmon Gate, Nikko (261) Thunder Devil of Nitenmon Gate, Nikko (262) image of Nio at Nikko (263) stone image pool of Gaman, Nikko (264) Nio, or Guidance (265); carvings on the Yashoman, Nikko (266) Okusha (shrine) at Nikko (267) Karamon Gate, Nikko (268) Karamon Iyemitsu Temple, Nikko (269) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Japan, Kyo-do, Nikko (270) Dainichido at Nikko (271) rickshaw drivers in front of a European-style hotel (272) waterfall, Yumoto (273) road to Chuzenji, Nakajaya at Nikko (274) Ganman, Nikko (275) artists tinting photographs (276) women cooking (277) women eating (278) Yashamon Gate, Nikko (279) stable at Nikko where sacred white pony is kept... (280) temple gateway guarded by lions (281) carved cat in chapel at Nikko (282) Nikko gateway (283) one of Nikko's many temples (284) shell gatherers near Yokohama (285) coolies carrying passengers across a stream (286) men in a boat (287); trees near Tokyo (288) Maple Leaf Tea House, Tokyo (289) tea plantation (290); "the prettiest girl in Japan" (291) pagoda at Nikko (292) women washing, drying, and ironing (293) "old time" Japanese warriors (294) a vegetable vendor (295); women reading (296) woman picking tea (297); "preparing for stormy weather" (298) bamboo garden (299) two women and a mirror (300) a young priest (301) two women and a mirror (302) women spinning (303) carpenters of Japan (304) fresh vegetable (305) riding in a kago (306) "little housekeepers" (307) women with dusters and brooms (308) the koto and samisen (309) other musical instruments (310) musicians (311)p ublic wrestling match (312) close view of sumo wrestlers (313) "judicial Hara-kiri" (314) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Japan and Algeria, Women posing for pictures in the shade (315) "a bit of Yoshiwara Yeddo (or Edo) (316) "sometimes called 'birds in a cage;" (317) women preparing vegetables (318) in a Japanese kitchen (319) women at dinner (320) two men "eating macaroni" (321) "coolies at luncheon" (322) people from North Japan (Ainu?) (323) studious girls (324); writing by the light of a paper lantern (325) koto and samisen or lyre and banjo of Japan (326) geishas (327) young dancers (328) Japanese children (329) theater street, Yokohama (330) basket merchant (3310- village scene (332); view at Nagasaki (333) Temple of Mayasan, near Kobe (334) cave near Nagasaki (335) postcard advertising indigenous embroidery, Algeria (Box 3, Folder 12)
- SERIES II: Correspondence
  - Letters, 1886-1888 (there is also a small photograph glued into this volume)--At sea, Paris, Rome, Pompeii, Naples, Florence, Venice (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1892-1894, Kansas City, Missouri San Francisco, California Portland, Oregon Tacoma, Washington Honolulu, Hawaii Yosemite, California Los Angeles, California Antwerp, Belgium Dover, England Paris London (some sketches) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1895, New York Nice, France Greece Alexandria, Egypt Jerusalem Paris (with menus and a stamp) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1897-1899, Bombay, India Dehli, India Benares, India Calcutta, India Rangoon, Burma Colombo, Ceylon Hong Kong Shanghai, China Osaka, Japan Yokohama, Japan Dublin, Ireland Chester England Paris (Box 4, Folder 4)